<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kovtun Lab on MemTraLab</title>
    <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kovtun Lab on MemTraLab</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://192.168.0.88:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Jane Smith</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/people/smith/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/people/smith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I joined the Kovtun Lab in 2023 as a postdoctoral researcher after completing my PhD in Neuroscience at Stanford University. My research focuses on understanding how membrane trafficking contributes to neuronal function and dysfunction in neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My current projects involve investigating the role of endosomal sorting in maintaining synaptic health and how defects in this process may contribute to Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease. I use a combination of super-resolution microscopy, live-cell imaging, and molecular biology techniques to study these processes in primary neuronal cultures and iPSC-derived neurons from patients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. Oleksiy Kovtun</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/people/kovtun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/people/kovtun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a Professor of Cell Biology specializing in membrane trafficking mechanisms. My research focuses on understanding how proteins and lipids are transported between different cellular compartments, with a particular interest in how these processes go awry in neurological disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I received my PhD from Harvard University in 2010, followed by postdoctoral training at the MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology in Cambridge, UK. Before starting my own lab, I worked as a research scientist at Genentech, where I developed an interest in translating basic cell biology discoveries into therapeutic applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Doe</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/people/doe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/people/doe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a third-year PhD student in the Molecular and Cell Biology program. I joined the Kovtun Lab in 2023 after completing my undergraduate degree in Biochemistry at UC Berkeley, where I first became fascinated with cellular logistics during a summer research project on endocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My dissertation research focuses on the molecular mechanisms regulating endocytosis in polarized cells. I am particularly interested in how cargo selection at the plasma membrane is coordinated with downstream sorting events. Currently, I am characterizing a novel adaptor protein complex that we believe plays a crucial role in this process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Research Grant Awarded</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;new-research-grant-awarded&#34;&gt;New Research Grant Awarded&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce that our lab has been awarded a new research grant to study membrane trafficking in neurological disorders.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://192.168.0.88:1313/img/grant-ceremony.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Grant Ceremony&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-focus&#34;&gt;Research Focus&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This grant will support our investigation into:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The role of endosomal sorting in neurodegenerative diseases&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Novel therapeutic targets in membrane transport&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Development of imaging techniques to visualize membrane dynamics&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for updates on this exciting new project!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Discovery: Novel Regulator of Endosomal Sorting Identified</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/new-discovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/new-discovery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lab has recently identified a novel protein complex that plays a crucial role in regulating endosomal sorting. This discovery, published today in Nature Cell Biology, sheds new light on how cells maintain proper protein trafficking pathways.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;blog-figure&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;img src=&#34;http://192.168.0.88:1313/img/blog/endosomal-sorting.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Endosomal sorting pathway&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 1: Schematic representation of the endosomal sorting pathway highlighting the newly identified regulatory complex (in red).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Endosomal sorting is a fundamental cellular process that determines the fate of internalized proteins, directing them either for recycling back to the plasma membrane or for degradation in lysosomes. Defects in this process have been implicated in various neurological disorders, including Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s and Parkinson&amp;rsquo;s diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lab Awarded $2.5M NIH Grant for Neurodegenerative Disease Research</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/grant-awarded/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/grant-awarded/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce that our lab has been awarded a $2.5 million grant from the National Institutes of Health (NIH) to study membrane trafficking defects in neurodegenerative diseases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcoming New Graduate Students to the Lab</title>
      <link>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/new-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://192.168.0.88:1313/blog/new-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to welcome two new graduate students to the Kovtun Lab this semester.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
